### RAMKUMAR RAJARAM



splendidramkumar@gmail.com



+65 83358047



https://www.linkedin.com/in/ramkum ar-rajaram-758291129/

https://ramkumarrajaram.github.io

#### **SUMMARY**

Experienced Information Technology Analyst with a demonstrated history of working in the information technology and services industry. I have worked as a Full Stack developer in both Web and Android mobile Development and skilled in Java, JavaScript, Kotlin, Spring framework, RX Java, React Js, Node.js, Amazon Web Services, RESTful Web Services and well versed in Extreme Programming concepts such as Test Driven Development (TDD) and Pair Programming with good analytical, logical and decision making skills.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## FULLSTACK ENGINEER SINGAPORE AIRLINES

JAN 2020 to Present

- I. As a Full stack engineer, responsibilities include creating mobile and web applications and implementing the backend architecture with no compromise in the quality and performance. Best practices such as Test-Driven Development and Behavioral Driven Development are adopted with more emphasize on SOLID principles and Design Patterns.
- 2. Develop frontend applications using Java, Kotlin for Android with Dagger framework and React and Redux frameworks with TypeScript for web development
- 3. Develop backend applications using Java, Node.js, Spring framework, SQL, GraphQL and WebSocket
- 4. Pair with developers to ensure each and every line of code is tested, reviewed and refactored with quality and to ensure 100% test coverage
- **5.** Responsible for granular commit/push the deliverable to repository using GIT version control
- 6. Deliver and deploy developed deliverables to Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic Beanstalk and Crashlytics via Continuous Integration / Continuous Delivery pipeline in Jenkins for DEV, UAT and Production environment
- 7. Work on ad hoc chores/POCs for requirements proposed by Product owners/Client
- 8. Ensure continuous learning by participation in events such as Code Kata, Hackathons, Lunch 'n' Learn and encourage team members to involve in such events

# INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY ANALYST | FULLSTACK ENGINEER TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

JAN 2017 to SEP 2019

- I. Responsible for developing high performance, quality deliverables by adopting industry's best practices such as Test-Driven Development (TDD), Behavioral Driven Development (BDD), Object-Oriented Programming, Agile methodologies, SOLID principles, Design Patterns, Functional Programming, Continuous Integration / Continuous Delivery etc. for Full stack application with emphasis on Android and Backend development
- 2. Develop application using languages Java, Kotlin, JavaScript (React and Node.js), SQL and frameworks such as Spring, Hibernate and Dagger
- 3. Responsible for developing backend application with microservices using Spring boot and RESTful web services and Android Mobile application using Java/Kotlin

#### **SKILLS**

#### Languages

Java, JavaScript, Kotlin, HTML5, CSS, SQL, TypeScript

#### Frameworks/Libraries

Spring, Hibernate, ModelMapper, RxJava, Junit Framework, Mockito, Espresso, Jest, Mocha and Chai

#### **Tools**

IntelliJ, Android Studio, Visual Studio Code, Eclipse, Maven, Gradle, MySQL Workbench, SQL Developer, WebStorm, Pivotal Tracker, JIRA, Splunk, Jenkins

#### **Databases**

MySQL, SQLite, Cassandra, DynamoDB

#### **Environments**

MAC OS, Windows

#### **Version Control**

GIT and SVN

#### **Cloud Technology**

Amazon Web Services

- 4. Pair with one of the developers in the team daily to ensure each and every line of code developed is tested, reviewed and refactored to ensure better quality
- 5. Responsible for granular commit/push the deliverable to repository using GIT version control
- 6. Deliver and deploy developed deliverables to Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic Beanstalk and Crashlytics via Continuous Integration / Continuous Delivery pipeline in Jenkins for DEV, UAT and Production environment
- 7. Create POCs for requirements proposed by Product owners/Client
- 8. Responsible for proposing appropriate solutions to the requirements and have peer discussions on how to improve the efficiency of the application
- 9. Ensure continuous learning across team members by organizing sessions such as LUNCH AND LEARN, Code Kata and encourage developers to enroll in such events
- 10. Good team player

## SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER - FULLSTACK TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

JUL 2014 To DEC 2016

- I. Responsible for developing high performance and quality deliverables for E-Commerce web applications for clients
- 2. Develop application using languages Java, HTML, CSS, JSP, JavaScript, SQL and frameworks such as SPRING and Hibernate in an Agile environment and follow best practices and principles of the software industry
- 3. Responsible for reviewing the code and mentoring the junior developers
- 4. Responsible for pushing the changes and deploy them to different stages of testing such as DEV, SIT, UAT and Production environments with agile methodologies
- 5. Responsible for analyzing the requirements stated by the client
- 6. Create POCs and propose best possible solutions for requirements proposed by Product owners/Client
- 7. Responsible for leading and taking ownership of the product and working closely with the product and QA team for quality delivery
- 8. Responsible for driving the sprint to meet the timeline

#### **SOFTWARE ENGINEER**

#### **TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES**

DEC 2012 To JUN 2014

- I. Responsible for developing web applications using Java, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JSP and frameworks such as Spring and Hibernate
- 2. Responsible for analyzing and providing optimal solutions to the requirement and get them reviewed by senior engineers
- 3. Responsible for delivering projects under waterfall SDLC model

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING 2008 - 2012**

Anna University, Chennai

Bachelor's Degree in Electrical and Electronics Engineering,

CGPA – 8.78, First Class with Distinction

#### PERSONAL DETAILS

Age : 29

Date of Birth : 05 – February - 1991

Passport : K4512856

Permanent : 361/6, Rajiv Nagar, Third Street, Kovilpatti

Address - 628501

Current Address : #03-26, 781, Upper Changi Road East,

Singapore, 486069